<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-02T17:00:08+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Michal Stanke</title><subtitle>Michal Stanke (Mikk or MikkCZ) - working for Cisco Systems, member of OpenAlt, proud Mozillian from the Czech Republic.
    </subtitle><author><name>Michal Stanke</name></author><entry><title type="html">Linux pro babičku</title><link href="/2021/01/24/linux-pro-babicku.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Linux pro babičku" /><published>2021-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2021/01/24/linux-pro-babicku</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/01/24/linux-pro-babicku.html">&lt;p&gt;V týdnu mi zavolali rodiče, že se jich babička začala ptát na nepříjemné otázky, a jestli bych s tím nemohl něco udělat, že si nevědí s odpověďmi rady. &lt;em&gt;„Jaký je rozdíl mezi Linuxem a mojí e-mailovou schránkou?“&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;„Musím se přihlásit k e-mailu, než jdu na internet?“&lt;/em&gt; A jestli bych pro ni mohl vytvořit nějaké hezky nadepsané složky s odpověďmi na její otázky a třeba i trochou víc informací, aby jí to vystačilo i chvíli do budoucna.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Takhle, moje babička už trochu s počítačem umí. Svůj první a zatím jediný dostala od tety po tom, co si teta pořídila nový. Dokoupili jsme do něj tehdy pár součástek, nainstalovali načisto Windows 7, a začali babičku učit s myší. Klávesnici už zvládala, v práci psala na stroji. Počítač ale na Windows 7 úplně nestačil, takže jsem je po chvíli nahradil za Linux Mint, který jsem tehdy sám používal. Dneska už by to byla asi nějaká verze Fedory.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Mint má hlavní panel a nabídku od základu dole stejně jako Windows, a kdybych to babičce neřekl, prý by si myslela, že jsme jí jen změnil tapetu a barvy na lištách. V tomto případě s prostředím MATE běžel dosti svižně, takže babička byla spokojená. Dodnes používá hlavně webový prohlížeč (e-maily, trochu Googlu a proklikávání odkazů) a po této stránce jí nic nechybělo.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Po tom, co vloni na podzim babičce doporučili na očním pořídit si místo &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20210124000000/https://www.nokia.com/phones/cs_cz/nokia-3310&quot;&gt;Nokie 3310&lt;/a&gt; „pořádný“ telefon s velkým displejem, aby na něj viděla, si začala doma zkoušet starší chytrý Samsung po mámě. Zjistila, že je to skoro jako počítač a začala se zajímat i o něj, co a jak funguje, a tím se dostáváme zpátky na začátek.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Jak už tedy víte, prohlížeč webové stránky už babička zvládá, dokonce bez obtíží používá používá můj oblíbený operační systém Linux, a tak jsem se rozhodl, že jí onu příručku připravím elektronicky. Na nějaké kurzy se dřív přihlásit nechtěla, a dneska to zase kvůli COVIDu nejde.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Zatím mám za sebou první dva dny tvorby &lt;a href=&quot;https://linux-pro-babicku.stanke.cz/&quot;&gt;Linuxu pro babičku&lt;/a&gt;. Rozhodl jsem se použít &lt;a href=&quot;https://rust-lang.github.io/mdBook/&quot;&gt;mdBook&lt;/a&gt;, protože s ním mám byť drobnou tak dobrou zkušenost z mého přispívání do lokalizace Mozilly. Taky je napsaný v jazyce Rust, kterému fandím. Obsah píšu v Markdownu s trochou HTML, ale v případě potřeby nebude problém vše zkonvertovat do jiného formátu nebo vytisknout. Vytvořit &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/MikkCZ/linux-pro-babicku&quot;&gt;repozitář na GitLabu&lt;/a&gt;, nastavit mdBook a napsat první krátkou kapitolu jsem zvládl už včera.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Dneska jsem pokračoval dalšími kapitolami a moc mě to baví. Nebude to kdovíjaká encyklopedie, ale babičce a možná jako úvod do nějaké nudnější hodiny informatiky na základní škole by to mělo stačit. Taky doufám, že by příručka, stejně jako tenhle článek, mohla někomu posloužit jako důkaz, že Linuxu na domácím počítači se vůbec není potřeba bát. Zatím ale zdaleka není hotovo, minimálně polovina kapitol chybí, a tenhle a asi ani příští víkend je dokončit nestihnu.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Pokud vás taky zlobí někdo jakékoliv věkové katergorie s otázkami na základy práce s počítačem, zkuste &lt;a href=&quot;https://linux-pro-babicku.stanke.cz/&quot;&gt;Linux pro babičku&lt;/a&gt; a dejte mi vědět, jak se vám líbí. Budu rád za všechny připomínky, opravy chyb a návrhy na zlepšení. A pokud chcete sami zkusit Linux a nevíte jak na to, přečtěte si k tomu ještě &lt;a href=&quot;https://proc.linux.cz/&quot;&gt;Proč Linux&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michal Stanke</name></author><category term="web" /><category term="linux" /><category term="czech" /><summary type="html">V týdnu mi zavolali rodiče, že se jich babička začala ptát na nepříjemné otázky, a jestli bych s tím nemohl něco udělat, že si nevědí s odpověďmi rady. „Jaký je rozdíl mezi Linuxem a mojí e-mailovou schránkou?“ „Musím se přihlásit k e-mailu, než jdu na internet?“ A jestli bych pro ni mohl vytvořit nějaké hezky nadepsané složky s odpověďmi na její otázky a třeba i trochou víc informací, aby jí to vystačilo i chvíli do budoucna.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jekyll on Czech OSS communities websites</title><link href="/2019/01/12/jekyll-on-czech-oss-communities-websites.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jekyll on Czech OSS communities websites" /><published>2019-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2019/01/12/jekyll-on-czech-oss-communities-websites</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2019/01/12/jekyll-on-czech-oss-communities-websites.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; is a static site generator, which turns Markdown (almost plain text) or simple HTML stored in a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; repository into a static website. By &lt;em&gt;static&lt;/em&gt; I mean there is no scripting language like PHP running on the server, so you don’t need to worry about some villain taking it over to send spam or mine coins. All you need for hosting your website built by Jekyll is a webserver somewhere, e.g. GitHub Pages.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In the small Czech pond of OSS communities the first Jekyll I saw was on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.l10n.cz/&quot;&gt;L10N.cz&lt;/a&gt;. The first time I ever heard about Jekyll and I fell fell in love immediately. L10N.cz uses Jekyll for its main site, basically a blog like this one. With the small group of authors, low cadence of posts and no comments, both WordPress or Drupal would be a huge overkill to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;My next Jekyll instances were already started by me. This blog, the list of Mozilla.cz slides and the default homepage for Czech users of SeaMonkey. Both the Mozilla sites are somewhat special and use leverage mostly the templating engine than any other Jekyll feature.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://prezentace.mozilla.cz/&quot;&gt;Mozilla.cz slides&lt;/a&gt; site uses Jekyll to generate the listing of various conferences and events we attend. In the repository, there are both the slides themselves, and their index in the form posts annotated with event names and links to video recordings. It’s no black magic and bare GitHub Pages are perfect for hosting this site without any additional tooling.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://start.mozilla.cz/&quot;&gt;default homepage&lt;/a&gt; for SeaMonkey is a little more complicated that it may look like. Small page which fits into a single screen, but not truly static - it’s regularly updated with new items from two RSS feeds. First I thought about going pure JS, but SeaMonkey users may block it and making them all download the feeds would not be friendly to the RSS feed providers either. So when rewriting it from PHP, I was forced to step into the unknown space of Jekyll plugins, and also start to build the site using Travis CI. GitHub Pages are really limited in the options for custom plugins or even regular rebuilds. I will unveil more details in some of the coming posts.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Recently I also started rebuilding two Linux community websites - &lt;a href=&quot;https://proc.linux.cz/&quot;&gt;proc.linux.cz&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubuntu.cz/&quot;&gt;Ubuntu.cz&lt;/a&gt;. Given the fact that probably I will be the only content author (at least for the beginning), I went for Jekyll again. Jekyll definitely does not fit all cases I can imagine, but I think static sites are &lt;em&gt;sexy&lt;/em&gt; and easier to maintain with very limited team resources than some outdated yet simple PHP scripts, or even full blown CMS. Actually it may be even easier for someone to fix bugs or typos in the content via PR, that sending a complex report over e-mail, what is wrong a where. Of course when you have some input from users or more content creators, WordPress or Drupal with their simple admin UI and access rights management are the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michal Stanke</name></author><category term="web" /><category term="jekyll" /><category term="english" /><summary type="html">Jekyll is a static site generator, which turns Markdown (almost plain text) or simple HTML stored in a git repository into a static website. By static I mean there is no scripting language like PHP running on the server, so you don’t need to worry about some villain taking it over to send spam or mine coins. All you need for hosting your website built by Jekyll is a webserver somewhere, e.g. GitHub Pages.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pontoon Tools for Chrome and more from Mozilla All Hands</title><link href="/2018/06/23/pontoon-tools-for-chrome-and-more-from-mozilla-all-hands.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pontoon Tools for Chrome and more from Mozilla All Hands" /><published>2018-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2018/06/23/pontoon-tools-for-chrome-and-more-from-mozilla-all-hands</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/06/23/pontoon-tools-for-chrome-and-more-from-mozilla-all-hands.html">&lt;p&gt;Pontoon Tools is an add-on to bring Pontoon, the Mozilla l10n application, into your browser. With the release of 3.2.0 today, I can officially announce &lt;strong&gt;support for Chrome&lt;/strong&gt; and Chromium based browsers! If you haven’t installed Pontoon Tools yet, you can do so from &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/firefox/addon/pontoon-tools/&quot;&gt;AMO&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/pontoon-tools/gnbfbnpjncpghhjmmhklfhcglbopagbb&quot;&gt;Chrome Web Store&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;As for functionality, there are not big features, but small improvements. The most notable is the introduction of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/mozilla.dev.l10n/930wIVcAyc0&quot;&gt;unreviewed state&lt;/a&gt; and some related improvements of the browser action popup. System notifications are now enabled by default, and when you click them, the related project or your team page will open.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/pontoon-tools-3-2-0.png&quot; style=&quot;display:block;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/pontoon-tools-3-2-0.png&quot; alt=&quot;Updated Pontoon Tools browser action popup&quot; style=&quot;max-height:250px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;During the previous week, I also had the opportunity to attend Mozilla All Hands in San Francisco and meet with the l10n-drivers team. My &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.mozilla.org/L10n:Meetings/SF-All-Hands#Michal&quot;&gt;agenda&lt;/a&gt; was packed by Pontoon Tools and we have agreed to start promoting it to more users this year. There are no dates yet, but you can expect more improvements and stabilization of Pontoon Tools in the next two or three months.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you want to keep an eye on what’s planned for Pontoon Tools and get involved in the plans, check &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.mozilla.org/L10n:Pontoon-Tools&quot;&gt;this page on MozillaWiki&lt;/a&gt; and the project &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MikkCZ/pontoon-tools&quot;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michal Stanke</name></author><category term="mozilla" /><category term="l10n" /><category term="webextension" /><category term="english" /><summary type="html">Pontoon Tools is an add-on to bring Pontoon, the Mozilla l10n application, into your browser. With the release of 3.2.0 today, I can officially announce support for Chrome and Chromium based browsers! If you haven’t installed Pontoon Tools yet, you can do so from AMO or Chrome Web Store.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Leaving Mozilla Reps</title><link href="/2018/04/28/leaving-mozilla-reps.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Leaving Mozilla Reps" /><published>2018-04-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-04-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2018/04/28/leaving-mozilla-reps</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/04/28/leaving-mozilla-reps.html">&lt;p&gt;The beginning of this year was a little hectic. Finishing master studies, deleting Facebook and seeking for a new job to finally get back to the same, only full time. All of this shifted my priorities a little bit and this Monday I informed my mentor that I would like to join the Reps alumni.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Let’s start with my master studies and Facebook first, because those two are pretty related. About two years ago, I decided to delete my Facebook account after I finish the university. I was using Facebook only to be in the school groups, discuss our assignments and share tips for exams. So after I finished my state exams, I asked Facebook to delete the account. The time proximity with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facebook%E2%80%93Cambridge_Analytica_data_scandal&quot;&gt;Cambridge Analytica scandal&lt;/a&gt; was just a coincidence. I always assumed that’s happening regularly on Facebook, and until today, I am not sure whether people were more surprised by the Cambridge Analytica thing, or that someone can consciously without any external motivation delete his or her Facebook account. Both seem pretty normal to me.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;But back to Mozilla related stuff. For weeks and weeks I was thinking about all my Mozilla activities and if I want to go on the same way - user support (SUMO + social media), localization, Mozilla presence on conferences, planning several other general localization events, attending other open communities events, plus all the local stuff around Mozilla.cz web, infrastructure and community. I didn’t even have enough time to write reports or blog posts about my activities, experience and lessons learned. After getting a full time contract in Cisco, I somehow naturally displaced those activities from the list, that I didn’t enjoyed anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;As a result, this Monday I informed Michael that I want to join the Reps alumni. I do not thing I can dedicate what’s needed to support the Reps goals and be a valuable and involved member.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/mstanke-reps-joined.png&quot; style=&quot;display:block;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/mstanke-reps-joined.png&quot; alt=&quot;The day when I joined Mozilla Reps&quot; style=&quot;border:0.1em solid gray&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, being a Rep for two years (per day exactly) was a really great experience. If you are an active Mozillian interested in organizing events or campaigns, joining Reps is the only right thing to do. Without me being a Rep, we would probably never started attending conferences so often nor making meetups. It really eased the start. I want to thank &lt;a href=&quot;https://reps.mozilla.org/u/michaelkohler/&quot;&gt;Michael Kohler&lt;/a&gt; as my mentor, the Reps council of course, and every single Rep who shared the experience with me through the program.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I am not leaving the Mozilla community, no way. I am still a Mozillian in the first place and I will still contribute the ways I believe I can do the best.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michal Stanke</name></author><category term="mozilla" /><category term="mozilla-reps" /><category term="community" /><category term="english" /><summary type="html">The beginning of this year was a little hectic. Finishing master studies, deleting Facebook and seeking for a new job to finally get back to the same, only full time. All of this shifted my priorities a little bit and this Monday I informed my mentor that I would like to join the Reps alumni.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mozilla.cz 2017 recap</title><link href="/2018/01/14/mozilla-cz-2017-recap.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mozilla.cz 2017 recap" /><published>2018-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2018/01/14/mozilla-cz-2017-recap</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/01/14/mozilla-cz-2017-recap.html">&lt;p&gt;This week I have published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mozilla.cz/zpravicky/ohlednuti-za-rokem-2017/&quot;&gt;recapitulation of the last year&lt;/a&gt;, how we did in 2017 and how we would like to continue in 2018. It was rather a short article in Czech and I would like to elaborate more here for the global Mozilla community.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In the last year we have attended more conferences than I realized. I was surprised when counting them before writing the post, and if I counted right, the final number is eight, plus a secondary school. Btw. did you know we started meetups too? Yes, we did! We call them MozBeers and so far we had them in Prague and Brno, the two largest cities in the Czech Republic. True, our MozBeers are not happening regularly, but we have them. Also I need to highlight we never gathered in the full count on any place, nor meetups nor conferences, but thanks we were able to share our experience and ideas, everything went smooth.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Localization became our natural activity we do not even have to plan or organize much. We have localized both versions of Firefox Focus for Android and iOS (kudos to Michal Vašíček and the rest of the team), all the new Tet Pilot experiments, and Firefox Quantum of course! I don’t want to boast, but retrospectively I think we could do even twice as much l10n work without even noticing.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;After such year I am pretty positive about our community traction. There are new faces around and I feel much less pressure on myself, which was not the case a year ago. Despite we still s**k in our communication in the direction outside, I see this improving in the last months. We have created a Telegram channel as an open channel to reach us in a completely informal way for all the Czech users and the broader community. Plus we have got &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.mozilla.org/sumo/2018/01/13/the-big-sumo-report-2017/&quot;&gt;Czech in the social support tool&lt;/a&gt;. @firefox now speaks Czech too! I hope we can improve in the area of communication in 2018 even more.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;There are several priority goals we are already decided to do in 2018:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Go through all the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/buglist.cgi?cmdtype=runnamed&amp;amp;namedcmd=Open%20[cs]%20bugs&quot;&gt;terminology bugs and questions&lt;/a&gt; we have filed on ourselves and resolve them.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Write a localization style guide. This is a long overdue task.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Finish all other, mostly technical &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mozilla.cz/ukoly/&quot;&gt;tasks&lt;/a&gt; we have.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Get Firefox.cz and Mozilla.cz in a new dress. No promises on this, but it seems to happen soonish.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Build a strategy for regular and interesting content for Mozilla.cz. This will be a tough one.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Show ourselves everywhere possible. ;)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;You already see there is plenty for us to do. I could barely complete a half of these tasks only myself, but I see them as a peace of cake being surrounded by the army of awesome Mozillians!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michal Stanke</name></author><category term="mozilla" /><category term="l10n" /><category term="mozilla-reps" /><category term="community" /><category term="english" /><summary type="html">This week I have published a recapitulation of the last year, how we did in 2017 and how we would like to continue in 2018. It was rather a short article in Czech and I would like to elaborate more here for the global Mozilla community.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pontoon Tools 3.0</title><link href="/2017/11/12/pontoon-tools-3-0.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pontoon Tools 3.0" /><published>2017-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2017/11/12/pontoon-tools-3-0</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2017/11/12/pontoon-tools-3-0.html">&lt;p&gt;After 150 commits in total, Pontoon Tools got a third major release 3.0! From now on, post-installation/update tour will show you the most important features in Pontoon Tools. So this time for the last time probably (and shortly) what’s new in the new and still shiny Pontoon Tools 3.0.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;As noted, there is a new introduction tour listing all major features of Pontoon Tools. It will appear after first installation or major version update. You can guess where I took inspiration for its design. Please check it carefully, as there may be feature you were not aware of before. ;)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/pontoon-tools-intro.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display:block;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/pontoon-tools-intro.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pontoon Tools introduction tour&quot; style=&quot;max-width:450px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Also a completely new feature arrived, which are system notifications. Pontoon Tools can now utilize the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/Add-ons/WebExtensions/user_interface/Notifications&quot;&gt;notifications API&lt;/a&gt; to inform you about new unread notifications in Pontoon. Because I understand not everyone must be happy with something popping up in the system, this feature is disabled by default and the introduction tour will allow you to enable it quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;And last but not least, I have unified the toolbar button popup style with Pontoon itself, and added short information about last team activity. The complete list of all the small improvements, including those on background, can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MikkCZ/pontoon-tools/releases/tag/v3.0&quot;&gt;release notes&lt;/a&gt;. If you are not using Pontoon Tools yet, your can &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/firefox/addon/pontoon-tools/&quot;&gt;install them into your Firefox from AMO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michal Stanke</name></author><category term="mozilla" /><category term="l10n" /><category term="mozilla-reps" /><category term="webextension" /><category term="english" /><summary type="html">After 150 commits in total, Pontoon Tools got a third major release 3.0! From now on, post-installation/update tour will show you the most important features in Pontoon Tools. So this time for the last time probably (and shortly) what’s new in the new and still shiny Pontoon Tools 3.0.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The story of me@mozilla</title><link href="/2017/10/20/the-story-of-me-at-mozilla.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The story of me@mozilla" /><published>2017-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2017/10/20/the-story-of-me-at-mozilla</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2017/10/20/the-story-of-me-at-mozilla.html">&lt;p&gt;After our successful presence on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linuxdays.cz/2017/&quot;&gt;LinuxDays&lt;/a&gt; conference in Prague, I have been asked by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linuxexpres.cz/&quot;&gt;Linux Expres&lt;/a&gt; for an interview, how I get to the Mozilla community, what I do there, etc. &lt;del&gt;The article is not public yet&lt;/del&gt; The article went out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linuxexpres.cz/rozhovor/michal-stanke-ceska-komunita-by-mohla-prosazovat-mobilni&quot;&gt;today&lt;/a&gt;, but I have realized I never told this story to the Mozilla community itself. So take some popcorn and make yourself comfortable…&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Back in times when I thought PowerPoint presentations are the masterpiece of computer science and their quality score is determined by the number of animations per slide, my Internet Explorer got sick. After an attempt to change the homepage in hope it will stop showing me ads everywhere, I have decided I need a new browser. I knew some people online and asked them for a recommendation, and their answers were Opera and Firefox. I never saw any of them in action before, so I dived into the dark unknown waters of the internet to download them for testing. My first impression from Opera was it’s too complex and complicated to change the homepage and import bookmarks, while Firefox did that all for me when I clicked all the &lt;em&gt;Next &amp;gt;&lt;/em&gt; buttons. The winner was clear.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;That was &lt;strong&gt;Firefox 2.0&lt;/strong&gt;, way different from Internet Explorer. When exploring the user documentation to help me a bit, I found an information, that 3.0 is imminent. Wow, a browser that is being developed and will have a new &lt;em&gt;version&lt;/em&gt;. Super cool for someone using the old IE! But the documentation did not helped me much actually, which drove me right into the registration form of the &lt;strong&gt;Czech community forum&lt;/strong&gt;, and here my community story begins.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;After some time, I realized that I know answers for other questions on the forum, so I started answering. About the same time I have decided to start using all Mozilla-based applications I can make use of, namely Thunderbird and Instantbird (which I &lt;strong&gt;started localizing&lt;/strong&gt; soon). Later the Mozilla.cz team offered me to translate some &lt;strong&gt;articles on SUMO&lt;/strong&gt; and websites like AMO, but for me the Czech community forum was still the top until 2014, when Pavel Cvrček (JasnaPaka) offered me to &lt;strong&gt;translate Thunderbird&lt;/strong&gt; on my own. That was huge responsibility for me, but also recognition. I thought that’s the most you can achieve, I felt like a real boss.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The next year, 2015, was like a big spinning wheel, outlined by the &lt;strong&gt;Mozilla.cz restart&lt;/strong&gt; initiative led by Pavel to rebuild the Mozilla.cz website content (and design) and utilize as much of Mozilla infrastructure as we can. The motto was “Mozilla is doing many things, and they do them right”, it’s not necessary to update own versions of user documentation anymore. The second half of the year was very turbulent. Pavel decided to forward me the responsibility for &lt;strong&gt;Mozilla.cz content&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Firefox localization&lt;/strong&gt;, leaving the community projects due to the lack of time. At the end of the year, the changes in the community probably became so visible, that I have been invited to &lt;strong&gt;Mozlando&lt;/strong&gt;, to meet my first non-Czech Mozillians in person.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The last two years I will sum in a sentence or two. I try to act like a community peer for every l10n and support related project in Mozilla, I became a Rep, and after our localization community grew over 4 people, I am unable to name all the milestones we have outlined and achieved. The last two years are not really a story of me@mozilla, but a story of &lt;strong&gt;czech-community@mozilla&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Now you may think that my involvement with the global Mozilla community is pretty short. And you are right. I am around the global stuff since 2014/15, still having longer experience with support forums answers than anything else. But for me that illustrates how powerful and dynamic the Mozilla community is.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michal Stanke</name></author><category term="mozilla" /><category term="english" /><category term="mozilla-reps" /><category term="community" /><summary type="html">After our successful presence on the LinuxDays conference in Prague, I have been asked by a Linux Expres for an interview, how I get to the Mozilla community, what I do there, etc. The article is not public yet The article went out today, but I have realized I never told this story to the Mozilla community itself. So take some popcorn and make yourself comfortable…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mozilla L10n workshop in Berlin</title><link href="/2017/09/26/mozilla-l10n-berlin-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mozilla L10n workshop in Berlin" /><published>2017-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2017/09/26/mozilla-l10n-berlin-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2017/09/26/mozilla-l10n-berlin-workshop.html">&lt;p&gt;The last weekend, a long list of Mozilla l10n communities gathered in the new Mozilla office in Berlin. Some notes from various sessions you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.mozilla.org/L10n:Meetings/2017_Berlin_Workshop&quot;&gt;find on the wiki&lt;/a&gt;. I have been present on sessions about Transvision, cross-channel repositories, Pontoon, Fluent, DevTools l10n and the localizer-developer dialog. I won’t cover the content of the sessions here, but if you’d like to discuss any of the topics, feel free to reach out to me. Instead I want to make few notes about the event organization itself and aside.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Let’s take it from the beginning. I haven’t prepared for the workshop at all. It took me few hours to manage all the stuff like communication with the agency and booking, but as for the format announced as &lt;a href=&quot;http://unconference.net/&quot;&gt;unconference&lt;/a&gt;, I did nothing. The question about topics was there during Friday dinner, but at the moment, I had only one topic in my mind. On Saturday, during the 15 minutes we have to propose topics, I wrote down five of six spontaneously. Still do not know, where they came from, probably thanks to the welcome and introduction session? &lt;strong&gt;Note 1: If you host and unconference, start with some breaking session to get people on the same page and warm them up.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;We were about 50 in total. How many localizers actually Mozilla has, when this was only one of six workshops this year? The number does not make such impression like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/t_chevalier/status/911518756576296960/photo/1&quot;&gt;packed room&lt;/a&gt;, huh… &lt;strong&gt;Note 2: I still know very little about the Mozilla l10n community, there are so many people I haven’t met with yet…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Unconference format is what I loved the most. The chosen sessions were actually what the attendees wanted, most of the discussion were on topic and everyone took active part. There was also enough time for breaks to reboot your brain flooded with information coming from all around. And the ping pong tournament? Well, it was something unexpected, but very very welcomed to relax. &lt;strong&gt;Note 3: Never forget to take a break.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Before coming to Berlin, I have put down a list of task we may want to do as a Czech community there. But the event program was so full of topics I wanted to attend, we have touched the prepared task only in conversation. This happened to me on all Mozilla events so far. &lt;strong&gt;Note 4: When going to some Mozilla event, it’s OK to prepare goals to achieve on your own, but do not rely on you will complete any of them, there is no free time to spend.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note 5: I want to do that again!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michal Stanke</name></author><category term="mozilla" /><category term="l10n" /><category term="workshop" /><category term="english" /><summary type="html">The last weekend, a long list of Mozilla l10n communities gathered in the new Mozilla office in Berlin. Some notes from various sessions you can find on the wiki. I have been present on sessions about Transvision, cross-channel repositories, Pontoon, Fluent, DevTools l10n and the localizer-developer dialog. I won’t cover the content of the sessions here, but if you’d like to discuss any of the topics, feel free to reach out to me. Instead I want to make few notes about the event organization itself and aside.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pontoon Tools 2.0</title><link href="/2017/09/13/pontoon-tools-2.0.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pontoon Tools 2.0" /><published>2017-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2017/09/13/pontoon-tools-2.0</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2017/09/13/pontoon-tools-2.0.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s 13th of September, but it’s not Friday so I hope Pontoon Tools version 2.0 will be the lucky one. I have uploaded it to AMO a short while ago, so the approval may take some time a before you get the update. But I promise, there are reasons for the major version bump. ;)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This version is dedicated to proofreading and quick bug reporting/fixing. Many times it happened to me, that I spotted a typo on a new Mozilla.org page and it took me dozen of clicks and page loads to open Pontoon a get the string fixed. For the same reason I haven’t pushed the rest of the team to proofreading much, because I know how complicated the reporting can be.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;With 2.0, all of this changes. On any production website, that Pontoon Tools recognize, you will see a page action icon in the address bar. When you spot a string to update, just click the page action and a new tab with Pontoon translation view of the corresponding project will open. For typos or unique texts, there is even faster way - select the text on the page, right-click it and in the context menu you will find a quick search option. Just &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mozilla.org/firefox/&quot;&gt;try it somewhere&lt;/a&gt;… Isn’t that handy?&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/pontoon-tools-page-action.png&quot; style=&quot;display:block;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/pontoon-tools-page-action.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pontoon Tools page action on Mozilla.org&quot; style=&quot;max-width:450px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/pontoon-tools-mozilla-org-context-menu.png&quot; style=&quot;display:block;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/pontoon-tools-mozilla-org-context-menu.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pontoon Tools context menu on Mozilla.org&quot; style=&quot;max-width:450px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The second big change are the add-on options, accessible from the Firefox Add-ons manager (or &lt;em&gt;Ctrl+Shift+A&lt;/em&gt;). I have reorganized them into sections and added few extra. If you were playing with the options before this version, some of your preferences might be lost now… But feel free to go ahead and set them up again. On the other hand if you are not sure about the changes you have made, you can reset all the options to their default values.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/pontoon-tools-options.png&quot; style=&quot;display:block;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/pontoon-tools-options.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pontoon Tools options&quot; style=&quot;max-width:450px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;At this moment, I am not decided about the next big things to come. Maybe there is no major feature missing after the initial takeoff? I am looking forward to hear your thoughts, either &lt;a href=&quot;https://mozillians.org/u/mstanke/&quot;&gt;directly&lt;/a&gt; or on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MikkCZ/pontoon-tools&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. It can be both positive or negative feedback, bug report or a feature request. :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michal Stanke</name></author><category term="mozilla" /><category term="l10n" /><category term="webextension" /><category term="english" /><summary type="html">It’s 13th of September, but it’s not Friday so I hope Pontoon Tools version 2.0 will be the lucky one. I have uploaded it to AMO a short while ago, so the approval may take some time a before you get the update. But I promise, there are reasons for the major version bump. ;)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mozilla Latest Version - my first project dedicated to Mozilla</title><link href="/2017/09/07/mozilla-latest-version-my-first-project-dedicated-to-mozilla.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mozilla Latest Version - my first project dedicated to Mozilla" /><published>2017-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2017/09/07/mozilla-latest-version-my-first-project-dedicated-to-mozilla</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2017/09/07/mozilla-latest-version-my-first-project-dedicated-to-mozilla.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MozillaCZ/mozilla-latest-version&quot;&gt;Mozilla Latest Version&lt;/a&gt; (shortly &lt;em&gt;Mozlv&lt;/em&gt;) was my first project I have written entirely because of Mozilla. It’s a WordPress plugin to get the latest version number of Firefox/Thunderbird/SeaMonkey and the corresponding links for download or release notes. Currently it loads data from ship-it (&lt;a href=&quot;https://product-details.mozilla.org/&quot;&gt;product-details.mozilla.org&lt;/a&gt;), but it existed even before ship-it started to export this data to public. And at this moment, I am giving &lt;em&gt;Mozlv&lt;/em&gt; some love again. ;)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;It all started at the beginning of 2015, few months after Pavel Cvrček (JasnaPaka) outlined and kicked off the so called “Mozilla.cz restart”. We have reviewed all the content on the Mozilla.cz website (OK, it was mainly done by Pavel), reduced it and redirected outdated pages to SUMO articles and other appropriate sites, that were update regularly. We have also replaced the old &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mozilla.cz/zpravicky/plnime-slib-a-tak-je-tu-novy-web-mozilla-cz/&quot;&gt;Mozilla Europe like looking theme&lt;/a&gt; for customized One Mozilla design. But despite making the whole website look new and shiny, we were still left with one big problem under the hood. The problem was in new Firefox versions being release every ~6 weeks. Each time a new version of Firefox or Thunderbird had been released, we needed to put it into WordPress. Of course, we had some plugin to update all the download links and version numbers across all pages, but we needed to watch the new releases on our own and paste them into the fields in administration.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Luckily we have realized soon there are several JSON files on mozilla.org and svn.mozilla.org containing exactly the information we needed. March 2015 was the month when &lt;em&gt;Mozlv&lt;/em&gt; was born. It took me actually many hours, because PHP was my greatest enemy back then. :D After I have finished the plugin, there were no earth-shaking changes there. Yes, Firefox for Android and iOS were added, yes, ship-it replaced files placed on the svn server, but there were no bigger features, not even needed. Most of my commits were about fixing breakages.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;About a week ago, you may have noticed, that I have added few commits and released version 2.0. “Oh, new major version! There must be plenty of new stuff there, right?” No, there is not, but I have been pretty lazy in bumping the versions in the past, deploying individual commits to Mozilla.cz. Making 2.0 sounds appropriate to me when there is a version actually working after so long. And this time &lt;em&gt;Mozlv&lt;/em&gt; will hopefully serve another “community restart” - Mozilla.sk. In Czech Republic we see Slovakia like our brothers. I am helping for some time to &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=639192&quot;&gt;revise the content&lt;/a&gt; and soon we want to pick a new Mozilla theme too. But there will be one more thing… you are right… updates of Firefox download links. The difference from Mozilla.cz is, that on Mozilla.sk we want to not just switch to &lt;em&gt;Mozlv&lt;/em&gt;, but also display an archive of previous Firefox releases. That’s something not implemented in the plugin and I hope to find some time to do it this autumn. And as a bonus, I have discovered there is an AMO JSON API, that would allow us to display information about features extensions from AMO too!&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mozlv&lt;/em&gt; is my first project and after more than two years, I am surprised the code is still used somewhere, even more it seems to get extended by two quite big features soon and be deployed to a new website. If you run a community website on WordPress and deal with updating Firefox versions manually, try Mozilla Latest Version. The code is available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MozillaCZ/mozilla-latest-version/&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and if you encounter any issues with deployment, feel free to get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Michal Stanke</name></author><category term="mozilla" /><category term="wordpress" /><category term="english" /><category term="mozilla-reps" /><summary type="html">Mozilla Latest Version (shortly Mozlv) was my first project I have written entirely because of Mozilla. It’s a WordPress plugin to get the latest version number of Firefox/Thunderbird/SeaMonkey and the corresponding links for download or release notes. Currently it loads data from ship-it (product-details.mozilla.org), but it existed even before ship-it started to export this data to public. And at this moment, I am giving Mozlv some love again. ;)</summary></entry></feed>